all right AI is here AI has been here
for a while and people are losing their
jobs in Tech right now and a lot of
people are asking the
question uh how do I keep my job with AI
being so good at writing code and doing
my job and it's a pretty simple answer
so I'm just going to put it out there
and then we'll talk about it the answer
is AI is not taking your
job not unless you should have already
lost your
job um it's not it's not AI has nothing
to do with you losing your job as a
software developer it just means you
have to change the way you do the
job honest to God it really does and I'm
probably somebody's going to you know do
hate here so there's a couple of
explanations here the first one is the
recent like batch of of this is 2024
this is the month of May end of May 2024
and we're coming off the end of a bunch
of layoffs because we had a big Tech
Bubble Burst uh which included Bitcoin
like right um and that was what we've
been going through that we've been I
think we're kind of covering according
to the economic numbers we're going
through something of an economic
recovery right now um and this is from
Fox News Financial analysts reporting
these these numbers that nobody can lie
about economically in America anyway we
are kind of back on the upswing doesn't
feel like it but we are and with regard
to Tech there's been a lot of people
losing their jobs but I'm going to argue
that a lot of those people would have
lost their jobs anyway and it doesn't
have anything to do with AI um and I I
feel like AI is getting blamed for um a
lot of the job losses that are happening
right now and in fact the reason the job
losses are are happening are much more
complicated than that and it it's not to
say that we've got you know a lot of
lazy programmers and software developers
who didn't keep their skills up that's
also not it um the nature of employment
as I talked about in another video
please go watch that video the nature of
employment is based on trust and it's
based on demand and need and um I did
another video about how to survive late
stage capitalism it's a very
controversial video people put all kinds
of bad comments there and let me just
summarize we are every time i' I've seen
three bubbles burst now and every time
we do all the Developer jobs go away
because all the money uh to fund all
those new companies and new developer
job jobs and new new things goes away
there's just no money for new projects
but so they take the money away and they
put that money that they have into
keeping things running keeping the
lights on and that's operations and so
that's why you see people in operations
in infrastructure support and AI support
or HPC high performance Computing
support which is what my job is um
maintaining and you see systems
developers and systems integrators you
see them keeping their job because
they're not making new fancy SI
projects that are going to win a bunch
of you know new money and you know new
they're not they're not looking for new
value and new products they're looking
for making their existing systems more
efficient which means if you want to
stay a developer during a bubble
bursting like that the best place to be
is a backhand systems Integrations
developer because these people like me
are currently in the process of
modernizing their existing systems and
making them better and keeping them
running in you know fixing the the
ancient bugs that they've had these that
that demand doesn't pay very high but I
mean it pays enough I I make plenty but
the point is that those jobs those those
you know Integrations jobs and those
backend type of jobs and the the sort of
Maintenance coding kind of jobs those
jobs stay they stay very strong all
throughout the entire time and so if you
look at all of the different uh jobs
that are being lost right now and the
people say oh lost my job I lost my job
usually always they were working for an
edgy you know Silicon Valley company or
they were working on a project um so I
have a story about this um and we'll get
back to the AI thing so I was I was
hired at IBM like and I I on I was in
training I was hired by a in the
financial sector to do Java development
and the bubble burst while I was in
training and I had to re regroup and go
get another job and I've done I've
talked to told the story before but and
I was able long story I was able to
Parlay my Linux skills from working in
the garage uh building my own Linux
boxes and you know setting up my own
mail servers and stuff into a job and I
was able to keep that Junior Unix
administrator job um and and grow that
and then and then when the economy got
good somebody said hey don't you code
and they said we got this coding thing
we're doing for operations you want to
be on the team I said yeah sure so then
I was doing coding again the point is is
that by learning by learning the
fundamental skills of operations and and
knowing code and bring things together
you'll always have a job no matter what
I guarantee it you'll always have a job
if you keep those skills fresh and if
somebody lets go of you you will take
your toolbox and you'll go someplace
else and work there and you're your the
stuff that you have your your toolbox is
going to make you safe um most of the
people that come into my twitch chat and
say hey I lost my job what do I do now
so many of them are they're you know
they they they code and they only know
how code or they spent they spent time
learning like typescript and that's it
right or a web dev or something and you
know and webdb is extremely volatile
place to be I would never to be fair I
got started a little bit in webdb but I
would never ever ever work in web
development applications development
because it's just way too volatile the
landscape is changing too fast um the
the applications that come out are are
Fly by Night and when they'll be here
one day and they'll be gone the next um
the companies that are doing them
usually have really unusually high
demand for stuff and by the way this is
where AI comes in again because a lot of
those tasks that software developers are
doing right now in my opinion they're
going to be made easier by
AI so you know generating a framework
for a go project for you know to get
started right rather than making a
template repo and copying it and all
that stuff you probably will be able to
get good with you know send sending the
prompt the way you need it to
to have it like write all the
scaffolding for you for all that stuff
so the you know AI is never going to get
good enough to it can help you write um
you know the beginning part of of a I
don't know recursive you know parsing
Loop some sort of you know recursive
descent parsing parser Loop you know and
you might not know how to do that or you
might not want to do it every time so
rather than like defining a macro AI is
going to allow us to do those kind of
things and that's great that's
absolutely fantastic but that does not
replace the software developer who has
to say here's the kind of software I
want this idea that you're going to be
able to create an entire system you know
from scratch uh that does everything you
ever wanted it to that if that ever does
happen AI will have had to approach near
natural intelligence before we can do
that and the amount of data that would
have to be present inside of such an
application would be you know crazy and
I don't think we're anywhere close to
that personally I don't think within the
next 10 years I don't think the AI is
everever going to be that good um I
really don't and there's always going to
need I mean even even with a human now
right even with a several humans now
there's still bad code that gets through
and people who are well educated who who
don't and AI is going to be able to
catch those problems that's going to be
nice right so you'll be able to have
some some complex problem and then be
able to say you know here's the thing so
so let's end with the advice that I
would have for somebody who's lost their
job um first of all you didn't lose your
job to AI I mean I think I made that
point pretty well if you don't agree
that's fine I'd love to hear what you
have to say in the comments or anything
but that's not the reason the the reason
is probably because one you're working
for a company that is does not have a
sustainable future and it's more about
finding the right company than it is
finding the right Tech skills even
though I think it's kind of both right
you could be highly paid well
well employed programmer for the next 5
years programming in Cobalt if you
wanted to there is that there are that
many opportunities for that particular
job it just depends on what you want to
do I think a lot of times that people
that are losing their jobs are not
losing the jobs because because you know
somebody kicked them out of their job
there is a lack of demand but I think
it's also sometimes a part of the part
of people not quite being where they
need to be right because if you're if
you're really where you want to be and
you're doing what you really love uh and
you're not just you know checking the
boxes of what you think you want if
you've really done the work put in the
work to figure out what it is you want
to do there's a good chance you're going
to be one of the best at what you do and
if that's true then there's a good
chance you're going to know what things
are going to impact that job in advance
and you would not but way before the ax
is going to come and um you know there
are the completely random downsizing
actions that take place that that people
just fire whoever makes the most money
on the team and they don't even consult
with anybody about their skill set and I
mean God Twitter did that and they about
cripper the entire company because that
does happen but it's it's you know if
that does happen to you and you're one
of the good ones or you kept your skills
up then you know go do something else
should you learn AI yes you absolutely
should I think everybody should learn
how to make a model they should learn
how to support a model um they they
should learn how to run their own model
they should learn how to create their
own models using the existing tools and
I I I think that that is a fundamental
skill for all of technologists and in
fact I'm still struggling with how to
add it myself um but I do think that we
need to add uh we need to add some of
this stuff to the beginning of the
beginner boost people need to understand
how to prepare I mean even if the bottom
line is making sure you know how to code
a python you you it doesn't matter if
you like python or not python has become
the language of AI models period there
that's just not there's no debating it
at this point there there was some
debating it and I made several videos
about this about 5 years ago saying that
I felt like go could could take over for
P from python in the in the pytorch in
tensorflow space and and that was based
on uh articles that were being written
by professional um you know 10x AI
people that were saying that they prefer
go over python that's why I said that
but I think in 2024 it's pretty clear
that if you want to do anything uh data
related you got to know python as as
horrible as python virtual machines are
and and the lack of I mean all the
things that I hate about python doesn't
matter it doesn't matter because python
has has been elected to be you know the
dominant language with regard to data uh
uh Python and R by the way R is another
one um if you're going to go into that
and if you're looking for um you know if
you really want to make Buu bucks as
they say I would learn if if you learn
if you learn how to make data models if
you're going to go to college for
something don't go look here's the thing
about should I go to college yes I think
you should I've been taken to task over
the recommendation which is kind of
against my earlier recommendation long
years and years ago that you didn't need
college which was coming from IBM and
all these other um Google and places are
saying hey you don't need a degree you
just need to prove you can do the job
and I'm like okay great and then Along
Comes you know actual science and
statistics Adam ruins college and they
said 30% more at every stage of their
career for those who have a degree so at
least get a piece of paper if you're
going to get a piece of paper might as
well get one that matters and if I were
you and you wanted to stay Tech related
I I wouldn't do this I I went to college
because and I had the you know the
MoneyWise yeah we struggled but I was
still not so strapped for money that I
couldn't so I learned Russian and I
learned something I wanted to learn I'm
really glad I did that and then uh I
mean at the time the the conventional
wisdom for college was you should go to
college uh and get a a liberal arts
degree and then you would supplement
that with a Masters or specialized
education particularly if you're going
into business and in the 80s it was all
about the NBA I didn't get an NBA but if
I had ever wanted to get an NBA I was
ready for that because the the the path
back then was get a liberal arts degree
in English or Communications or or
international business uh or you know
some sort of language and then then
layer on top of that an MBA and then you
know proceed to to own you know the
world I mean we're talking about greed
is good ERA that's the era I went to
school um but I don't if today there's
so much money and problems that if I
were unemployed and I were trying to
find a job or I had been let go for some
reason I would if I were going to
supplement my degree or if I were going
in fresh and I was going to pay for
college degree I would probably my me
personally um well first of all I would
I I would I don't like getting Tech
degrees so I can have a even better Tech
job I'm not that guy I'm you know it
took almost everything in me not to you
know get a lot ofre so that I could go
fight for environmental law uh or you
know to get some sort of outdoor degree
so I could become a forestry agent or
you know Ranger or whatever um you know
and that's why I learn languages because
I love travel and tourism stuff so so
I'm probably not a good but if you but
if you wanted to stay in technology then
I would probably do a pre aai degree and
obviously calculus is one of those um if
you can do that any math degree they're
the the industry right now is stealing
math math people they they're literally
pilfering like phds in math and and
senior Math highly tenure professors the
the AI Community is like stealing them
from the academic world by offering them
like 10 times their salary um because
there's such a high demand for very very
high-end mathematicians and
statisticians and people who can deal
with the data and manipulate it and and
people who can put together you know the
AI models that they're necessary for
training stuff like that so I don't know
if that interests you it doesn't me I
mean I I went through 300 level calculus
but I don't I never really intended to
do anything with it I'm I was always
wanting to just you know move around
stuff so uh is AI going to affect you
how do you what do you do by if if if
you think AI is affected you if you've
lost your job um regroup you make sure
you've got all the bases covered and and
you know the skill stack beginner boost
we're trying to cover all those bases um
you know the the fundamental bases uh
for most technologists and and and then
you know proceed to to specialize in
something that you you feel is going to
distinguish you there's still a 37%
increase in security analyst positions
that's going on field um their software
developers is increasing at a rate of
24% that doesn't mean those jobs are
going away they're just getting there
just there's more and more of a drought
and people cannot get the jobs so uh you
got to make sure you get I don't think
spending time with leak code is the
thing um unless you want a very specific
horrible job uh where they actually
value lead codee skills I don't think so
so I mean lead code is actually a really
good example of something that's going
to be destroyed by AI any any in my
opinion any job that that would benefit
from somebody who's got really great
lead code numbers would instantly would
be affected directly by the ability of
AI to do anything better than any Le Cod
programmer ever could and maybe Silicon
Valley and some of these stupid
companies that keep requiring leak code
interviews and and practice will come to
terms with the fact that that mere
mortal humans don't need to memorize
things that have already been well
codified into other algorithms elsewhere
that you know that just it's just not
it's not a requirement if it is a
requirement it's a requirement for a
very specific niche of people most of
the the jobs that are going unfilled are
the more boring
mundane um software development jobs
where you need to be creative and figure
out how to look at a system and fix a
problem problem but not necessarily
apply one of these you know recipes for
for an algorithm you're not going to be
building you know link list data
structures you're not going to you will
occasionally Traverse a a rooted node
tree to do something but nine times out
of 10 that code's going to already be
there and you just need to know that it
exists you don't need to be able to do
it quickly so I mean and if anything AI
has made that really really true um so I
don't know that's kind of a long video
but uh hopefully that'll help